Guide to the Records of the New York Foundling Hospital 1869-2009 MS 347
New-York Historical Society
- Series IV - Centers, Programs and Departments, Alphabetical, 1869-2008
  - Subseries IV.12 - Crisis Nursery, 1965-2004 (bulk 1982-2004)
    The subseries contains proposals, reports, minutes, memos, pamphlets, brochures, fliers, photographic prints, and clippings. The photographic prints include images from many years before the Crisis Center opened, of Dr. Vincent Fontana, who was instrumental in establishing the program. For further documentation of Vincent Fontana, see Fontana Center subseries.
    The Crisis Nursery was established in 1982 to provide free emergency crisis care to children and families. Beginning in 2001 it operated under the umbrella of the Fontana Center of the Foundling. Children up to age 7 (and some older siblings) could stay in the nursery up to twenty-one days (with some exceptions), and were provided lodging, medical care, clothing, meals, behavioral assessments, and supervised play sessions. Parents received counseling, crisis intervention, emergency funds, and referrals for additional services. The Crisis Nursery operated a 24-hour Parent Helpline for parents in crisis.
    - Crisis Nursery - Proposals and Evaluations, 1972-1989 (Offsite-box 25, Folder 1)
    - Crisis Nursery - Operations - Memos, reports, minutes, policies, circa 1983-2004 (Offsite-box 25, Folder 2)
    - Crisis Nursery - Pamphlets, Helpline flier, brochures, other publications, circa 1984-2001 and undated (Offsite-box 25, Folder 3)
    - Crisis Nursery - Research, circa 1993-2003 and undated (Offsite-box 25, Folder 4)
    - Crisis Nursery - Photographic Prints, circa 1965-1999 (Offsite-box 25, Folder 5)
    - Crisis Nursery - Clippings, circa 1969-2004 (Offsite-box 25, Folder 6)
  - Subseries IV.13 - Deaf Services, 1979-1999
    The subseries documents three different Foundling programs for deaf people: the Laurent Clerk Group Home (materials include notes, correspondence, proposals, and a brochure); Junior High School 47 (correspondence, memos); and the Deaf Infant Program (proposal, memos, correspondence, press release). The subseries also includes photographic prints from these programs, as well as miscellaneous deaf services materials, including pamphlets.
    - Deaf Services - Correspondence and Memos, 1979 October 30 - 1985 June 24 (Offsite-box 26, Folder 1)
    - Deaf Services - Laurent Clerc Group Home - Proposals, drafts, memos, flier, 1979 October 9 - 1982 June 28 (Offsite-box 26, Folder 2)
    - Deaf Services - Laurent Clerc Group Home - Notes, correspondence, brochure, 1980 January 15 - 1981 October 6 and undated (Offsite-box 26, Folder 3)
    - Deaf Services - Laurent Clerc Group Home - Correspondence/Proposals with Social Services for Children, 1980 January 15 - 1983 November 14 (Offsite-box 26, Folder 4)
    - Deaf Services - Junior High School 47 - Correspondence, memos, 1981 January 20 - 1984 December 19 (Offsite-box 26, Folder 5)
    - Deaf Services - Deaf Infant Program - Correspondence, memos, proposal, press release, 1983 April 4 - 1984 September 14 (Offsite-box 26, Folder 6)
    - Deaf Services - Miscellaneous Materials including pamphlet, circa 1982-1999 (Offsite-box 26, Folder 7)
    - Deaf Services - Photographic Prints, circa 1982-1996 and undated (Offsite-box 26, Folder 8)
  - Subseries IV.14 - East Harlem Neighborhood Center, 1975-1999
    The East Harlem Neighborhood Center began in 1975 as a foster care prevention program focusing particularly on adolescent and young parents. In January 1978 it moved to space on the ground floor of Lehman Houses on 110th Street. The program has provided assistance to families in the form of health, welfare, housing, and vocational services, individual casework and group counselling, education in parenting and household management skills, mini day care and respite services, and activity groups for teens.
    Materials include proposals, pamphlets, reports, clippings, and photographic prints. Most prints are circa 1976. See also Parents as Partners subseries.
    - East Harlem Neighborhood Center - proposals, pamphlets, invitation, 1975 April 3 - circa 1999 (Offsite-box 26, Folder 9)
    - East Harlem Neighborhood Center - manual, circa 1976 (Offsite-box 26, Folder 10)
    - East Harlem Neighborhood Center - annual report, 1977 (Offsite-box 26, Folder 11)
    - East Harlem Neighborhood Center - photographic prints, circa 1976, 1990 (Offsite-box 26, Folder 12)
    - East Harlem Neighborhood Center - clippings, 1990, 1994 (Offsite-box 26, Folder 13)
  - Subseries IV.15 - Family Day Care, circa 1968-1985
    The Family Day Care program, inaugurated in 1968, provided day care in private homes under the supervision of the Foundling.
    Materials include proposals, annual reports, pamphlets, a manual, clippings and photographic prints.
    - Family Day Care - proposals, manual, report, correspondence, pamphlets, circa 1968-1985 (Offsite-box 26, Folder 14)
    - Family Day Care - annual reports, 1977, 1980, 1981 (Offsite-box 26, Folder 15)
    - Family Day Care - photographic prints and clippings, 1968, 1969 (Offsite-box 26, Folder 16)
  - Subseries IV.16 - Vincent J. Fontana Center for Child Protection, 1949-2008
    The Vincent J. Fontana Center for Child Protection was established in 1999, and opened in a dedicated facility at 27 Christopher Street in Manhattan in November 2004. The Center was founded to provide community-based preventive services and therapy for children and families damaged by abuse and neglect, as well as training and education programs for child-care professionals. It also housed a research and devlopment department studying interventions against child abuse to discern best practices.
    The center was initiated by, and named after, Dr. Vincent J. Fontana, Medical Director of the New York Foundling Hospital from March 1962 until his July 2005 death. In his campaign against child abuse, he was the author of The Maltreated Child (1964) and Somewhere a Child is Crying (1973), among other books, articles and papers. He was also an allergy specialist.
    The subseries contains materials related to Vincent Fontana and to the Fontana Center. Materials are arranged chronologically and include many articles, books, and other materials by and about Dr. Fontana created prior to the institution of the Fontana Center. Documents specific to the center itself appear in the period 1999-2008. There are also circa 250 photographic prints of Dr. Fontana and the Fontana Center, arranged at the end of the subseries. A few other photographic prints in this subseries are housed in Box 27, Folder 4.
    See also Crisis Nursery subseries, for another child abuse program spearheaded by Vincent Fontana.
    - Dr. Vincent Fontana - Certificates of membership in medical societies (8 originals, 1 photocopy), 1949-1977 (Offsite-box 27, Folder 1)
    - Newspaper clippings about Vincent Fontana, child abuse, and related subjects, circa 1952-2002 (Offsite-box 27, Folder 2)
    - Dr. Vincent Fontana biographical material - clippings, honors, obituaries, correspondence, circa 1952-2005 (Offsite-box 27, Folder 3)
    - Dr. Vincent Fontana asthma work - brochures, clippings, reports, photographic prints, 1963-2005 (Offsite-box 27, Folder 4)
    - Fontana, Vincent J. The Maltreated Child: The Maltreatment Syndrome in Children (New York: Charles C. Thomas, 1964) (Offsite-box 124)
    - Miscellaneous articles by Vincent Fontana, circa 1966-2003 (Offsite-box 27, Folder 5)
    - Letters from the public regarding child abuse, circa 1966-2005 (Offsite-box 27, Folder 6)
    - Fontana, Vincent J. Somewhere a Child is Crying: Maltreatment-Causes and Prevention (New York: Macmillan Publishing Co. Inc., 1973) (Offsite-box 124, Volume 242)
    - Letters to the Editor by Vincent Fontana - published clippings and drafts, 1975-2001 and undated (Offsite-box 27, Folder 7)
    - The Catholic Lawyer, Vol.22, No.4, incl. "Child Abuse: Tomorrow's Problems Begin Today" and Villanova Law Review, Vol. 23, No.3, incl. "The Maltreated Child of Our Times" both by Vincent Fontana, 1976-1978 (Offsite-box 27, Folder 8)
    - Newspaper columns by Vincent Fontana, circa 1977-2003 (Offsite-box 27, Folder 9)
    - 11 Parents Magazine articles by Vincent Fontana, 1978 November - 1979 December (Offsite-box 27, Folder 10)
    - 6 booklets on child abuse by Vincent Fontana, 1978-1982 (Offsite-box 27, Folder 11)
    - Human Ecology Forum, Vol.8, No.4 and Vol.15, No.1 with articles by Fontana, 1978, 1984 (Offsite-box 27, Folder 12)
    - "Saving Children and Families" booklet including conference paper by Vincent Fontana, 1983 September (Offsite-box 28, Folder 1)
    - Pediatric Annals Vol.13, No.10, journal edited by, and with article by, Vincent Fontana, 1984 October (Offsite-box 28, Folder 2)
    - 12 issues of Missing/Abused, Vol.1, No.2 - Vol.5, No.1 (missing Vol.1, No.3 and 4 and Vol.4, No.1), Medical Editor Vincent Fontana, 1985-1989 (Offsite-box 28, Folder 3)
    - "Parent Consultations with Dr. Vincent J. Fontana," draft typescript manuscript, circa 1986-1999 (Offsite-box 28, Folder 4)
    - "High Risk Factors Associated with Child Maltreatment Fatalities," Mayor's Task Force on Child Abuse and Neglect, Vincent Fontana Chairman, 1987 January (Offsite-box 28, Folder 5)
    - Family Practice Recertification Vol.12, No.11, with article by Vincent Fontana p. 71, and Fontana on editorial board, 1990 November (Offsite-box 28, Folder 6)
    - Fontana, Vincent J. and Moolman, Valerie Save the Family, Save the Child: What We Can Do to Help Children at Risk (New York: Dutton, 1991) (Offsite-box 124, Volume 243)
    - Task Force on Youth in Crisis: reports, correspondence, clippings, 1996-2005 (Offsite-box 28, Folder 7)
    - Alumni Magazine of College of Medicine, SUNY Science Center Brooklyn, article by Fontana p. 4, 1998 (Offsite-box 28, Folder 8)
    - Fontana Center Capital Campaign Ad Hoc Steering Committee Volunteer Resource Manual, 1999 March (Offsite-box 28, Folder 9)
    - Fontana Center brochures, circa 1999-2005 (Offsite-box 28, Folder 10)
    - Fontana Center booklets for training program and for child care workers (2 each of 2 booklets), circa 2005 (Offsite-box 28, Folder 11)
    - Fontana Center donors - correspondence, clippings, 2000-2005 (Offsite-box 28, Folder 12)
    - Fontana Center public relations plan: "A Beacon of Hope for Children", 2003 October (Offsite-box 28, Folder 13)
    - Fontana Center - opening reception program, blessing, and inaugural newsletter, 2004 November 30 - circa 2005 April (Offsite-box 28, Folder 14)
    - The Beacon (Fontana Center Research Newsletter), 1st and 2nd issues (2 copies of each), circa 2005 and 2008 (Offsite-box 28, Folder 15)
    - Fontana Center Year-End Report packet, circa 2005 December (Offsite-box 28, Folder 16)
    - Brooklyn Child Watch program of Fontana Center - pamphlet, press release, flier, 2008 April and undated (Offsite-box 28, Folder 17)
    - Vincent Fontana and Fontana Center miscellaneous, 1966 and circa 2003-2005 (Offsite-box 28, Folder 18)
    - Vincent Fontana - Photographic Prints, circa 1950's - 1970's (Offsite-box 29, Folder 1)
    - Vincent Fontana - Photographic Prints, circa 1970's (Offsite-box 29, Folder 2)
    - Vincent Fontana - Photographic Prints, circa 1980's-2005 (Offsite-box 29, Folder 3)
    - Vincent Fontana - Photographic Prints, circa 1980's-2005 (Offsite-box 29, Folder 4)
    - Fontana Center - Photographic Prints, circa 2002-2005 (Offsite-box 29, Folder 5)
  - Subseries IV.17 - Foster Grandparent Program, 1966-1994
    The Foster Grandparent Program began as a federally-funded program created by the Johnson Administration's Office of Economic Opportunity in 1965, to enable retirees to earn a small income building one-on-one relationships with needy children. The Foundling has been a New York host agency for the program since its inception to the present. The federally-administered program is currently funded by the Foster Grandparent Program of the NYC Department for the Aging.
    Materials include correspondence, agreements, periodicals, clippings, and photographic prints.
    - Foster Grandparents Program - Correspondence, Agreements, Clippings, circa 1966-1988 (Offsite-box 29, Folder 6)
    - Foster Grandparents Program - Mater Dei Vol.12, No.2 - issue on foster grandparents, 1966 July-August (Offsite-box 29, Folder 7)
    - Foster Grandparents Program - The Sign National Catholic Magazine, Vol.46, No.5 - article on Foundling foster grandparents page 28, 2 copies, 1966 December (Offsite-box 29, Folder 8)
    - Foster Grandparents Program - RN Magazine, Vol.30, No.12 - Article on Foundling Foster Grandparents p. 60, 1967 December (Offsite-box 29, Folder 9)
    - Foster Grandparents Program - Photographic Prints, circa 1967-1994 (Offsite-box 29, Folder 10)
  - Subseries IV.18 - Guidance Clinic, 1972-1981 and undated
    This subseries consists of one folder.
    The function of the Guidance Clinic changed during its tenure as a Foundling program. Operating out of the Foundling's main building, it provided diagnostic evaluations and therapy, and at various times administered the Temporary Shelter, the Mother-Child program, the Abusing Parent and Child Unit, the Unwed Mother Unit, and the Special Services Unit. The clinic also served clients referred by other departments, such as children from Blaine Hall and foster children. Most of the services related to the Guidance Clinic are represented as subseries in this alphabetical series; please see these subseries for further information.
    - Guidance Clinic - annual reports, program description, administrative documents, 1972-1981 and undated (Offsite-box 30, Folder 1)
  - Subseries IV.19 - Housing, 1984-1988
    The subseries consists of materials related to the Foundling's efforts to address the issue of housing for homeless families and families with inadequate housing. It consists of four folders - the first contains the minutes of the Housing Resource Group and related materials, followed by three folders with minutes, reports, memos and other materials related to the development of Sister Cecilia Schneider Community Housing in the Hamilton Heights neighborhood of Manhattan.
    See also IV.36-Project Basement for more on programs in the Hamilton Heights community, and IV.46-West End Intergenerational Residence for more on housing for homeless families.
    - Housing - Minutes of the Housing Resource Group and related reports, manual, and memos, 1986 December 1 - 1991 October 15 (Offsite-box 30, Folder 2)
    - Housing - Development of Sister Cecilia Schneider Community Housing - minutes, memos, reports, correspondence, 1984 September 15 - 1988 December 12 and undated (Offsite-box 30, Folder 3)
    - Housing - Development of Sister Cecilia Schneider Community Housing - minutes, memos, reports, clippings, invitation, 1989 January 25 - 1990 August 23 (Offsite-box 30, Folder 3)
    - Housing - Cecilia Associates Limited Partnership Financial Statements and Auditor's Report, 1998 December 31 (Offsite-box 30, Folder 5)
  - Subseries IV.20 - Independent Living Program, 1985-1998
    The subseries consists of 5 folders related to a program, initiated in 1986, dedicated to helping teenagers discharged from foster care function independently, via life skills training, counseling and other support services. Materials include minutes, memos, correspondence, photographic prints, and calendars. See also St. Agatha Home.
    - Independent Living - Correspondence, minutes, other materials involving New York City and State, 1985 November 15 - 1996 July 11 and undated (Offsite-box 30, Folder 6)
    - Independent Living - Assessments, conferences, memos, clippings, circa 1986 February - 1999 July 9 (Offsite-box 30, Folder 7)
    - Independent Living - Human Sexuality Curriculum - Memos, correspondence with Archdiocese and others, related materials, 1990 September 11 - 1998 September 23 (Offsite-box 30, Folder 8)
    - Independent Living - Photographic Prints, circa 1989-1993 (Offsite-box 30, Folder 9)
    - Calendars of art made by youths in the Independent Living Program, 1991-1994 (Offsite-box 30, Folder 10)
  - Subseries IV.21 - Infant Stimulation Program, 1987-1988
    - Infant Stimulation Program - Memos, report, 1987 July 10 - 1988 February 22 (Offsite-box 30, Folder 11)
  - Subseries IV.22 - Ladies Auxiliary and other Fundraising Associations, 1869-1987
    The subseries contains materials related to four associations that raised money for the Foundling. Associations are arranged in alphabetical order.
    The Dongan Guild of N.Y. State Employees held annual Christmas parties and Communion Breakfasts, among other events, to benefit the Foundling. One folder of materials 1961-1974.
    The Gothams, Inc. was an association which held an annual debutante ball, of which the Foundling was sole beneficiary. Two folders of materials including photographic prints, circa 1948-1982.
    The Ladies Auxiliary was founded in 1869 simultaneously with the Foundling itself. The iconic cradle wherein mothers deposited babies was donated by the first president of the Ladies Auxiliary, Mrs. Caroline Gilbert Thebaud, who served as president until 1902. The Ladies Auxiliary's purpose over the years included, but was not limited to, sewing and knitting clothing for children at the Foundling, hosting benefits, and soliciting donations. Materials include by-laws, constitution and charter, a volume of minutes, correspondence, donation booklets, programs, reports, invitations, clippings, and photographic prints, 1869-1986.
    Lots for Little, Inc. was a thrift shop created for the benefit of eight Catholic organizations, including the Foundling. Members of the Foundling's Ladies Auxiliary volunteered at Lots for Little, and served as intermediaries between the Foundling and Lots for Little. One folder of materials 1960-1987.
    Other records of Foundling fundraising, excluding these four associations, may be found throughout the rest of the collection. See Series VIII-Events, for programs from Ladies Auxiliary-sponsored events.
    - Dongan Guild of NY State Employees - correspondence, invitations, programs, 1961 April 18 - 1976 October 31 (Offsite-box 31, Folder 1)
    - The Gothams Inc. - Correspondence, clippings, pamphlet, invitations to debutante balls, 1954 November 3 - 1982 February 9 (Offsite-box 31, Folder 2)
    - The Gothams Inc. - Photographic Prints, circa 1948-1959 (Offsite-box 31, Folder 3)
    - Ladies Auxiliary - Correspondence, donation booklet, program, reports, appeal, 1869 November 23 - 1932 December 9 (Offsite-box 31, Folder 4)
    - Ladies Auxiliary - By-laws, constitution and charter, circa 1905, 1926, 1954, 1969 (Offsite-box 31, Folder 5)
    - Minutes of the Ladies Auxiliary - Bound volume and interleaved sheets, 1922 January - 1935 May 14 (Offsite-box 31, Folder 6)
    - Ladies Auxiliary - Correspondence, invitations, appeals, clippings, 1935 May 14 - 1986 December 17 and undated (Offsite-box 31, Folder 7)
    - Ladies Auxiliary - Photographic Prints, circa 1959-1963 (Offsite-box 31, Folder 8)
    - Lots for Little Thrift Shop - Correspondence, brochures, report, invitation, 1960 June 17 - 1987 December 31 and undated (Offsite-box 31, Folder 9)
  - Subseries IV.23 - Lower East Side Runaways Project, 1973
    The subseries contains one folder documenting a proposed alliance with the Educational Alliance, Inc., for a residential-outreach program for runaways.
    - Lower East Side Runaways Project - notes, correspondence, memos, pamphlet, 1973 February 13 - 1973 December 12 and undated (Offsite-box 31, Folder 10)
  - Subseries IV.24 - Medical Board/Medical Department, 1901-1995
    The subseries contains minutes, by-laws, reports, correspondence, clippings, a residency certificate, and photographic prints of the Medical Board/Medical Department of the Foundling, 1901-1995. For related material, see Fontana Center subseries (IV.6), and St. Ann's Maternity Hospital volumes in Series XIV.8.
    - Medical Board - Minutes, By-Laws, Correspondence, Reports, Photographic Print, circa 1901-1962 (Offsite-box 31, Folder 11)
    - Blank certificate of completed service for resident physicians (oversize), circa 1900-1958 (Offsite-box OS 1, Folder 4)
    - Dr. Joseph O'Dwyer (1841-1898) - Correspondence and photocopied material about his work, 1934-1995 and undated (Offsite-box 31, Folder 12)
    - Dr. Joseph DiLeo - Memorial material, photographic prints, and Medical Insight Vol.5, No.5 (article on p.34), circa 1943-1994 (Offsite-box 31, Folder 13)
    - Reprints of professional papers by Foundling physicians, 1944, 1954 (Offsite-box 31, Folder 14)
    - Medical Department Annual Reports, 1977, 1981 (Offsite-box 31, Folder 14)
  - Subseries IV.25 - Mother/Child Program, circa 1969-2007
    This subseries contains minutes, memos, reports, correspondence, a pamphlet, and photographic prints. Many more photographic prints documenting the program may be found in Series XI, Visual Materials.
    The Mother/Child Program began operating in 1972, at the Foundling's main location. Throughout the decade, it expanded its service at that location, added a facility in the Bronx in 1979, and moved entirely to the Bronx in 1988. The program's purpose was to provide temporary residence for teen mothers, and to teach parenting and other life skills. In this respect, it bears a relation to earlier Foundling programs for unwed mothers, such as St. Mary's Shelter.
    For related programs in this series, see the subseries Agency-Operated Boarding Homes, Adolescent Girls' Unit, Bronx Teen Parenting, and Mothers' Social Service, arranged alphabetically in this series. For a history of St. Mary's Shelter, see Box 51, Folder 11.
    - Mother/Child Program - Correspondence, plans, minutes, memos, 1969 September 25 - 1981 October 5 (Offsite-box 32, Folder 1)
    - Mother/Child Program - Reports, 1977-1982 (Offsite-box 32, Folder 2)
    - Mother/Child Program - Pamphlet, circa 1988-2007 (Offsite-box 32, Folder 3)
    - Mother/Child Program - Photographic Prints, circa 1971-1995 (Offsite-box 32, Folder 4)
  - Subseries IV.26 - Mothers' Social Service/Commerford Residence, circa 1970-2001
    Scope and Contents
    This subseries contains reports, clippings, client work, and photographic prints.
    The Mothers' Social Service Program provided comprehensive services (pre-natal and post-natal) to pregnant young women and unwed mothers. It was connected to the Mother/Child Program (see subseries IV.25) and to the Commerford Maternity Residence in the main building of the Foundling at 590 Avenue of the Americas.
    For related programs in this series, see the subseries Agency-Operated Boarding Homes, Adolescent Girls' Unit, Bronx Teen Parenting, and Mother/Child Program, arranged alphabetically in this series. For a history of St. Mary's Shelter, see Box 51, Folder 11.
    - Mothers' Social Service - Annual Reports, 1977, 1980, 1981 (Offsite-box 32, Folder 5)
    - Mothers' Social Service/Commerford Residence - Miscellaneous reports, clippings, client work, circa 1993-2001 (Offsite-box 32, Folder 6)
    - Mothers' Social Service - Photographic Prints, circa 1970-1993 (Offsite-box 32, Folder 7)
  - Subseries IV.27 - Mott Haven Prevention Program, circa 1977-2007
    Materials in the subseries include proposals, certificates, pamphlets, storyboards for public service commercials, and circa 75 photographic prints, as well as negatives and contact sheets.
    The Mott Haven Prevention Program began as a school-based program in 1976, and moved to a dedicated building in 1990, providing preventive services such as counseling, advocacy, referral, youth groups, home-based casework, and drug rehabilitation to families in Mott Haven, the Bronx, to stabilize families and prevent foster care placement.